Oh, lonesome night.
And babbits bawling,
the wind biting the bone.
Wind like this...
...full of voices.
Ancestry howling at you...
...yibbering stories...
...all voices tied up into one.
One voice differing...
...one voice...
...whispering out there,
spying from the dark...
...that fangy devil...
...Old Georgie hisself.
Mm. Now you ear up close...
...and I'll yarn you about
the first time we met...
...eye to eye.
ZACHRY: Nay, this life of rotted luck
ain't no smileysome yarnie.
And rares time I ever fess
the secret of Sloosha's Hallow.
Adam, my bro'by law, and his son and me
be trekking back from Honokaa Market.
Was Adam's custom to kowtow his
ancestry with offerings and honorings.
Suddenwise...
...that fangy devil's eyes, I felt them.
ZACHRY:
Who there?
MAN:
Zachry.
Oh....
A darky spot you're in, friend.
Old Georgie?
Ain't no blade can protect you
from the True-true.
BOY:
Pa!
Jonas! Jonas, go! Go, go!
Zachry!
Zachry? Zachry!
Stay here.
Safe here.
Zachry!
Kona'll be feasting on Adam
and his boy by sunup.
ADAM:
Zachry!
No! Nay!
You say all'a time, yeah?
"The weak are meat,
the strong do eat"?
Father! Aah! Unh.
No! Jonas!
OLD GEORGIE:
The True-true is what that is.
ZACHRY: Whole Valley whispering about
the blood of Adam and his son on my hands.
But Rose and Catkin never believed
no yibbering, and stood by me.
Uncle Zach, look!
Yeah, I see them.
Prescients come bartering twice a year...
...their ships creep-crawling on waves...
...just floating on
the Smart of the Old Uns.
Barter'll be starting soon.
Yeah.
You must go find your ma.
What're you doing?
Ma says ya ain't been right
since Sloosha's.
Say I gotta keep eyewise on ya.
You minding me while I mind the goats.
I see.
Stump is, who's gonna mind your ma
at the Barter?
She got no tongue for haggling,
not like you and me.
Sure you're all right?
Swear'by. Be home for supping.
Why words slink'n slide off'a tongue
when we need them most?
If my tongue been more bold...
...could I'a stop all the diresomes
about to happen?
CATKIN:
Uncle Zach!
This my big bro I yarning about.
ZACHRY:
What's what, sis?
Spesh guest hosting.
Thank you for the kindsome host
of my Valley stay.
I ain't yaysoed this, Rose.
Abbess sayso a gift of great honor.
She can be hosting then.
I bring you gift, Zachry.
Need no gift from a stranger.
ZACHRY: Now kin 'n bros 'n half-strangers,
even the Abbess...
...all come knocking...
...to gape in wonderment, like Sonmi herself
were sitting in our kitchen.
Questions about Prescience and their
woahsome ship poured thick 'n fast.
How your ship slide 'n glide
so silentsome?
Fusion engines.
No one queried what
"fusion engines" was...
...because they didn't want to look stupid
front of the gathering.
Fusion engines.
True really was,
Meronym answer the questions...
...but no answer ever quenched
your curio.
All that answering done was teached
everyone fo not trust her.
Nay, not a flea.
She a sly one.
Scheming and worming herself in.
Watch her, watch her close.
She's got secrets.
-Zachry Bailey!
-Sorrysome for waking you, Abbess.
I dream something
diresome's gonna happen.
Come in, come in.
ABBESS:
Oh, let Sonmi guide your heart.
Oh, I can hear her voice a'prayin’ for you.
Oh, Old Georgie's a'hungerin'
for your soul.
Oh. I know'd it.
-Spit'n cuss on your dreams.
-l know'd it.
"Bridge a'broken’, hide below.
Hands'a'bleedin’, can't let go.
Enemy's sleeping, don't slit that throat."
An auguring.
Oh, Zachry.
Trust Sonmi.
Keep Her warning with you.
Nail it to your memory.
Thank you. Thank you, Abbess.
Thank you.
WOMAN:
I found an old Transway marker, captain.
It's got to be the right mountain.
Problem is, the Valley people
are afraid of it.
They think the devil lives up there.
I can't find anybody to guide me
through the Kona territory.
Meronym...
...every day you are out there,
you increase your RAD levels.
This dream of yours is going to kill you.
And for what? The off-world colonies
may no longer exist.
I gotta go, captain.
How is it'n, Zachry?
Samewise.
MERONYM:
Mindin' some comp'ny?
ZACHRY:
Nay.
But goats'n surlywise herders
ain't known for our howziting temper.
Feelin' I ownin' you a real kowtow
for 'vadin' y'house with no sayso.
True sorrysome.
Fuggit, done's done.
MERONYM: So, you mindin' a stranger
queryin' ‘bout your troddin'?
Swap you, query for query.
Fair'by.
Cog y'ain't come t'learn stitchin'
or milking or herding.
Why you here?
I needing a guide.
Guide? To what?
Mauna Sol.
ABBESS:
"Bridge a'broken, hide below."
What's wrong?
The auguring come true, Abbess.
Broke bridge just like you say.
Meronym were there yibbering
about trekking up Mauna Sol...
...horses'pess’'n, woman come
cussing n'twisting up my life?
Mind the Words o'Sonmi.
-Abbess, come quick. It's the Bailey girl.
-Catkin?
Aye. She dying.
-What happened?
ROSE: Zach!
-Sonmi....
-The scorpion fish.
Healer say she be gone by sundown.
Ain't right, ain't fair
but nothing to be done.
Catkin's dying!
-What?
-Trod on a scorpion fish.
You can save her. You got spesh smarts
in that gearbag what'll save her.
That's the True-true.
Prescient Council swear
by special order...
...say I can't go play Lady Sonmi
for every fate twistin' wrong...
...n" click fingers make right.
I just a stupid goat herder, but I cog
you killin' Catkin by not acting...
...just as if I left you up on that bridge,
you Kona meat.
If a Prescient be laying with poison
melting her heart'n'lungs...
...If it be your kin?
Why's a Prescient's life
worth more'n a Valleysman?
I'll take you to Mauna Sol.
I know the way.
If you save Catkin...
...I will guide you through the devil's door
if that's where you want to go.
Mama?
Huh?
I hungry.
ROSE:
Oh, baby.
Something praying on you, Zachry?
You really ain't feary 'bout meetin'
Old Georgie on the summit?
More scaresome ‘bout the weather
than any devil.
You cog he's real?
Who tripped the Fall,
if not Old Georgie?
True-true?
The Old Uns.
That's jus' a rope o' smoke.
Old Uns got the Smart.
They mastered sick and seeds...
...mak'd mir‘cles 'n fly ‘cross the sky.
True. All true.
But they got somethin' else.
A hunger'n their hearts,
hunger that's stronger'n all their Smart.
Hunger? For what?
A hunger for more.
Okay.
Sussin' them clouds, we run out time.
Hey, don't need no smart rope.
Yea.
See you fall, I catch you.
You treddn' on the Devil's ground now,
Vall'ysman.
I'm sayin’ jus' once.
That offlander ain't gettin' to the top.
Time for you to let go of that rope.
You trespass, you pay the price.
Now drop that rope.
Drop that rope!
OLD GEORGIE:
Now drop that rope.
Let go of that rope! Let go of that rope!
ABBESS: Hands'a'bleedin’, can't let go.
OLD GEORGIE: Let go.
ZACHRY:
Hands'a'bleedin’...
ABBESS: Can't let go.
-..don't let go. No.
Thank you, Zachry.
You saving me twicely now.
You fall, I'll catch you.
ZACHRY:
Nay, the dead never stay dead.
Open your ears 'n they never
stop a'yibberin'.
What is this place?
Before the Fall,
Old Uns built dwellings...
...beyond the sky,
among the stars, and...
...this place joined here with there.
Sonmi....
'Tis she.
The Old Uns prayed to Senmi
same as Valleysmen?
Nay, not ‘cisely same.
What'd you mean down there, ‘bout...
...the Old Uns and Valleysmen
prayin' to Sonmi, not ‘cisely the same?
I mean, they were differing.
Differing.
How?
You want the True-true?
MERONYM:
Sonmi weren't no god.
She died hundreds of years ago
on a faraway pen'sula deadlanded now.
What?
I cog Valleysman b'liefs'.
I know Abbess teach'd you Sonmi was
a mir'cle, birthed o' Darwin Ged o' Smart...
...but ain't the True-true.
OLD GEORGIE:
Lies.
Her life was sad 'n judased.
She died tryin' to change
the Old-Uns thinkin'.
Lies, nothin' but lies.
Nay, nay, you're lyin'.
Sonmi?
'Fore she died, she spoke
of her acts 'n' deedins.
Her words a heartsake blessin'
minder'me what's the True-true.
How long you lissin t'this?!
How long you jus' stand there
an' let a stranger...
...keep fuckin' your b'liefs up ‘n down,
and in 'n out?!
MERONYM:
Zachry.
You o'right?
Finish your sussin'.
Oh, yeah, you ain't let go that rope
cause you a lustin'...
...for that darkly, sweet'meat.
Ah, cog it all now.
This whore, with her cokeynut skin...
...'n her slywise mask,
smilin' n wormin' her way...
...so you trust n bring her here...
...scavin n sivvin for what?
For what, fool?
They want the island.
Prescients want it all.
You judasing your kin for a piece of ass.
She ain't your tribe!
She ain't even your color!
This Jezebel ignores
your yarns and ways...
...spinnin‘ and spoutin' her whoahsome lies,
and you lap it up like a dog in heat!
It ain't true.
Ain't it? Then do sumthin’, stop her!
Take your spiker and...
[IN DEEP DISTORTED VOICE]
...slit her throat.
[IN NORMAL VOICE] Protect your tribe!
Protect your sis and little Catkin!
Kill her now 'fore it's too late!
Unh! Can't cog it.
Words and worrins like a wasp's nest
poke'd and prod'd by you!
You come elbowing in my life,
yibberin' about the True-true...
...an' never telling the whole true.
I need to cog what you're doing!
I told you. I come to send a plea o'help.
Help, why?
To steal our land?
To kill and slave us all?
What you want?!
Prescients dyin’, Zachry.
Jus' like Catkin.
This world poisoned me and all my kin.
We get no help,
find no home offland away.
I sayso truesome, we not s'vive.
We not s'vive.
Cross your fingers and toes.
If your prayer be answered...
...will Prescients never return
to the Valley again?
Those wishin' to come with us
be welcome.
The Valley is my home.
What was that?
Kona war cry.
Zachry!
Oh, no, no, Sonmi, no!
Nay.
No.
Rose.
ABBESS:
Enemy's sleeping, don't slit that throat.
Oh. Oh. Here, here, Catkin.
Oh. Oh, Catkin. Oh.
-Shh.
-No.
Zachry.
CATKIN:
Unc'a Zach!
ZACHRY:
Hide, hide!
ADAM:
Zachry!
No! No! No!
You kill chief. Now you meat.
ZACHRY:
Catkin.
-Safe now.
CATKIN: Unc'a Zach!
Safe, safe now.
Thank Sonmi.
No, thank you.
-Okay.
MERONYM: Thank you.
DUOPHYSITE:
Corporal, update the log book...
-...and make sure there is a cabin....
-Captain say-soed take you with us.
I wanna go with Meronym.
Go where?
Prescients n'same boat as us.
Got no home neitherwise.
Nay...not yet.
You think someone geoing to hear
your prayer, come down from the sky?
P'haps. P'haps one day.
Heh. One day ain't but a flea o' hope.
Yay, and fleas ain't so easy to rid.
ZACHRY:
Hm.
Well, firey dyin'.
Mm. Just as well. My yarning is done.
CHILDREN:
No! Please!
BOY:
Tell us one more!
MERONYM: Come on in here, you
little buggers! Come on, it's gettin' cold!
Uh, now, you heard your Grammy.
Go on. Get on with ya. Come on.
Eh? Eh?
You like it out here, don'tcha, Grampy?
Supposin' it minders me
of my Valley, huh?
Which is Earth?
Uh.... There.
That one there. That blue shimmerer.
Yeah.
Now, help your Grampy up.
Oh, yeah.
Are you gonna tell us
‘bout the woahsome ship...
...and the big sleep
and all the nex'nexs?
ZACHRY: No, your grammy tells
the nex'nexs way better than me.
Do you still love Grammy?
Your grammy is the best thing
that ever happened to me.
ZACHRY: Mm.
MERONYM: Come on here, Grampy.
Lemme warm them old bones.
[English - US - Future speak]